NYSUT Field Services Department Files. 6174/004
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- Syracuse Legal Correspondence, 1984 (Box 18, Folder 11)
  Memos re 3020a charges; memos re hiring of an uncertified person with a temporary coaching license, instead of a physical education teacher and freshman basketball coach who applied for the position, as a varsity basketball coach at Auburn Enlarged City School District; memos re case against Liverpool Central School District re creation of middle school tenure area, excessing of teacher due to declining enrollment; Freedom of Information Law request to Onondaga Community College re negotiator's contract; memos re investigation of assignment of teacher at Hamilton Central School District, poor performance review; memo re effort to reinstate Onondaga-Madison BOCES custodian, forced to resign for stealing soda; memo re assignment history of teacher seeking tenure at Port Byron Central School District; question of whether use of teacher aides is legal for study hall supervision, "outbreak" of practice in Madison County; request for legal review of use of teaching assistants to substitute for teachers at Onondaga-Madison BOCES; full-time appointment of adult education teachers at same, without probationary status, contractual benefits, or Social Security payments; Improper Practice Charges
- Utica Legal Correspondence, 1984 (Box 18, Folder 12)
  Request for legal assistance for special education teacher at Herkimer BOCES re tenure; letter from Mohawk Valley Community College Professional Association president to NYSUT president Tom Hobart, expressing dissatisfaction with NYSUT general counsel Bernard Ashe for declining to take appeal of case; memo re appeal to Commissioner re abolition of full-time dental hygienist positions in Utica City School District; state Supreme Court order denying grievance by music teacher against (Herkimer) Poland Central School District over part-time status, shift assignments; 3020a case in Richfield Springs; case of unsuccessful 3020a charges in Oriskany School District, reassignment of teacher to study hall from physical education "for safety of students," according to district, question of whether assignment was in effect disciplinary; request by the Mohawk Valley Community College Professional Association for legal assistance in pursuing Freedom of Information request re school district's finances for 1981-83; material re teacher at Auburn High School who swore at former school board president, was reprimanded, then sued school board members and superintendent; memo re improper denial of tenure in Oriskany Falls district; material re promotion dispute at Herkimer County Community College; Improper Practice charges
- Western Legal Correspondence, 1984 (Box 18, Folder 13)
  Memo re Improper Practice Charge in Tonawanda re replacement of two practical nurse-teachers with registered nurses; memo re improper suspension of Tonawanda teacher; other Improper Practice Charges; request for legal assistance in requesting binding arbitration over grievance at Erie BOCES re replacement of seven tenured health occupation positions with staff outside the bargaining unit at hourly wage; memo re 3020a case (conduct unbecoming: unreasonable corporal punishment) at Starpoint Central School District; material re 3020a case in Pine Valley (inappropriate physical contact); other 3020a cases; memo re retirement incentive program at Cheektowaga-Maryvale Union Free School District; legal memo in layoff and tenure case in Niagara Falls; memo re removal of disciplinary letter for custodian in Randolf Central School District; memo re anticipated strike by Niagara Association for Retarded Citizens
- Albany Legal Correspondence, 1984 (Box 18, Folder 14)
  Memo re unemployment insurance appeal for denial of benefits during extended recess period (Linda Gottstein); materials re coerced waiver of tenure in East Greenbush (Paula Quenelle); PERB decision in Queensbury Union Free School District and Mildred Campp et al. and Queensbury Non-Teaching Employees Association, NYSUT, re decertification petition; legal brief prepared by NYSUT in Queensbury case; Adirondack Community College record of staff appearances since June 1984, contact and service reports, with attached memo to Jim Conti noting constant contact by field representative; memos re Whitehall district teachers, expanded workload in violation of contract, request for injunctive relief; memo re 3020a case (alcohol consumption) in Wells, with newspaper clipping; memos re East Greenbush retirement incentive program; local assistance agreement between NYSUT and Greenwich Teachers Association
- Albany Legal Correspondence: East Greenbush (Gail Hill), 1985 (Box 18, Folder 15)
  Arbitration award; memo from NYSUT legal counsel noting error in mailing brief to wrong address, recommending court action
- Albany Legal Correspondence: Greenwich (Traver and McClay), 1985 (Box 18, Folder 16)
  Correspondence re litigation against the Greenwich Central School District to affirm credit for years of service of two teachers
- Elmsford Legal Correspondence, 1985 (Box 18, Folder 17)
  Letter to NYSUT president Tom Hobart from music teacher at Tappan Zee High School re grievance over removal from position as band director, related correspondence; memo re dismissed EEOC charges against NYSUT by teacher in Spring Valley; request for legal help from a long-term teacher at Spring Valley Senior High School (member of East Ramapo United Teachers Association), re lack of access to the sick bank, previous illnesses, with memo from Jim Conti advising against providing assistance; memos re Port Jervis strike; memo re Blind Brook teacher planning to return to work following surgery, using artificial voice box, possible issues with superintendent
- Mid: Hudson Legal Correspondence, 1985 (Box 18, Folder 18)
  Materials re 3020a charges against teacher at Red Hook Central School District (misconduct, inappropriate physical contact), teacher at Onteora Central School District (misconduct, alcohol), teacher at Windham-Ashland-Jewett Central School (misconduct, marihuana), teacher at Wappingers Central School District (incompetency, neglect of duty, conduct unbecoming), teacher at Hyde Park (conduct unbecoming, disclosing test question), two teachers at Pine Plains (conduct unbecoming, molestation), teacher at Rhinebeck (repeated drunkenness), teacher at Dover-Wingdale (shoplifting), teacher at Millbrook (conduct unbecoming, physical and verbal abuse); memos re legal action to compel Arlington school district to assign full-time teaching position to tenured teacher in seniority case; memo re commencing legal action to have letter of reprimand removed from Ulster BOCES teacher's file; correspondence re grievance re denial of usage of sick bank days at Monticello; question of tenure at Livingston Manor; unemployment benefits decision at Wappingers; correspondence, briefs, arbitrator's award, and related materials re suspended bus driver (Paul Martin) at Wappingers; material re revocation of teaching certificate for teacher (Angela Batorsky) at Cairo-Durham, denial of second year of maternity leave, question of retaliation by school district
- Nassau Legal Correspondence, 1985 (Box 18, Folder 19)
  Memos for cases re NYS retirement incentive program; maternity leave and tenure; concern by unmarried school monitor over possible dismissal by Port Washington school district upon discovery of her pregnancy, NYSUT intention to defend in a human rights proceeding; request for legal opinion re tenure of health teacher at Oyster Bay-East Norwich; question re legality of public school teachers providing services to parochial schools; memos re rights under Fair Dismissal Law of probationary teachers terminated early at East Rockaway and Rockville Centre school districts; memo re teacher accused of using corporal punishment, Garden City school district; memo re possible marital discrimination case of football assistant coaches who had applied for head coach position and believed they were turned down because they were married; memo re contract language re sick leave at Manhasset school district; question re deferred sabbatical leave at Port Washington; memo re complaint by teacher at Baldwin school district re violation of first and fourteenth amendment rights after accusing district of violations of Toxic Substances Control Act; memo re teacher who pled guilty to grand larceny for mismanaging funds for summer program at Locust Valley, potential 3020a charge
- North Country: Legal Correspondence, 1985 (Box 18, Folder 20)
  Request for legal opinion re rights of art teacher at Jefferson-Lewis BOCES; memos re teacher at Salmon River school district re free speech issue; materials re apparent illegality of retirement plan at Malone school district; memos re Parishville bus driver; memos re tenure for probationary teacher with poor initial performance evaluations, St. Regis Falls school district, question of harassment for involvement in strike; legal briefs re Westport school district requirement for medical report in sick leave absences, agreement between district and teachers association; grievance and related materials re pay issue in St. Regis school district
- NYC Legal Correspondence, 1985 (Box 18, Folder 21)
  NY Supreme Court decision, Langham et al. v. State of New York, dismissing dual enrollment health insurance case based on statute of limitations; cover memo form NYSUT counsel noting intent to appeal
- Rochester Legal Correspondence, 1985 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  Materials re unemployment insurance case (Gail Muir) in Hilton; memos re grievance over sex discrimination in salaries at Monroe Community College; legal brief by teacher (Linda Baker) against West Irondequoit School District and West Irondequoit Teachers Association, seeking damages from NYSUT, following resignation and failure of union to represent her in grievance; memo re possible part-time job assignments for teacher coming off two-year unpaid maternity leave, preservation of legal rights; memos re abolition of job in Rush-Henrietta school district; NYSUT legal counsel review of Cayuga-Onondaga BOCES interpretation of Garcia case under Fair Labor Standards Act, related materials; memo re permanent certification of teacher who obtained master's degree but failed to apply, Spencerport, related memo re period of amnesty, related briefing paper proposing change in state requirements; request for legal interpretation of law re fringe benefit payments for school employees released to serve in officer positions in bargaining unit (Webster school district); Improper Practice Charge for Wayne-Finger Lakes BOCES threat that teacher requests for union representation at disciplinary hearings would result in formal reprimand; PERB decision dismissing petition to decertify Greece United Substitute Teachers Organization (GUSTO); memo re question of tenure at Hilton school district; memo re decision not to pursue litigation over job assignment of art teacher in Spencerport school district; material re layoff/recall rights in Webster school district; 3020a cases
- Southern Tier Legal, 1985 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  Memorandum re incidental teaching of health education by teachers not certified in health, with attached NY Supreme Court ruling on the matter; materials re rights of teachers leaving employment for service in the military, re-employment rights; 3020a cases; memo re reassignment of math teacher to different school; seniority/tenure rights issue in Elmira, with attached lists of staffing changes; memo re liability for $100 shortfall by tax collector for Elmira City School District; 3020a charge against teacher in Bath Central School District, for insubordination (taking unpaid leave to extend ski vacation); review of legality of Workers' Compensation provision of contract between Spencer-Van Etten Teachers Association and school district; PERB brief in the matter of Newark Valley Cardinal Bus Drivers, NYSUT Local 4360, charging party, and Newark Valley Central School District, respondent, Exception to Administrative Law Judge's Decision and Recommended Order on Behalf of Newark Valley Cardinal Bus Drivers, re health insurance coverage
- Suffolk Legal, 1985 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  Material re arbitration in termination case by William Floyd United Teachers re Nancy Barton; memo and earlier correspondence outlining areas of concern to be discussed at meeting with NYSUT legal counsel by teachers from Elwood school district re forcing teacher to change a grade to zero for student cheating on test, also questions of seniority and the excess list; memo re EEOC complaint against United Teachers of Harborfields re age discrimination in negotiated retirement incentive; notice of claim and related memo re seniority list, recall rights at Kings Park school district; letter from field representative to legal staff re Lindenhurst teacher in dispute over reimbursing shortfall of $117 to Honor Society because of poor fundraising said to be his fault, previous record in personnel file of minor non-teaching infractions; correspondence between Westhampton Beach Secretaries Association, the Superintendent of Schools, and NYSUT field representative re ability and liability of secretaries to care for sick children in absence of school nurses, written policy on administration of medications; affidavit in NY Supreme Court in support of order to show cause on motion for preliminary injunction with temporary restraining order in the matter of Port Jefferson Station Teachers Association v. Board of Education, Brookhaven-Comsewogue Union Free School District, re unilaterally altering collective bargaining agreement re terms and conditions of employment; memo re Kings Park teacher denied disability retirement; memos re complex seniority issue at Huntington re tenure-area appointments; 3020a case at BOCES II-Suffolk involving 38 charges of incompetency and related problems; 3020a cases in East Islip and West Babylon re absenteeism; letter to Patchogue-Medford Congress of Teachers president re drug testing; material re Smithtown arbitration between BOCES 3 Faculty Association and BOCES 3, denying grievance re preferred eligibility list, three excessed teachers; correspondence re longstanding lawsuit over retirement credit in Amityville, request for help in expediting resolution; memo re seniority, question of whether special appointments count toward accrual, with attached case law citations (Bayport/Blue Point Teachers Association); materials re 3020a case (inappropriate remarks and physical contact), including handwritten answers by teacher, Bay Shore school district; memo re Selden Junior High School teacher believed to be suicidal, confronted by team of psychologists for two hours in principal's office, forcibly detained and escorted by police for involuntary admission to hospital, then told not to return to teaching until he arranged ongoing treatment, question of violation of rights; extensive materials re arbitration award re terminal leave pay, North Babylon Teachers Organization, including timeline of events, memos re political and personal issues with arbitrator, October 1984-February 1985; memo re case involving challenge to policy, upheld by U.S. Supreme Court decisions, allowing school districts to compel teachers to display Christmas trees in their classrooms, plans for involvement by American Civil Liberties Union, January 7
- Syracuse Legal, 1985 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  Memo re grievance over lost accumulated sick time after recall from preferred eligibility list at Cheektowaga district; memo re inability to file a notice of claim of injury for exposure to asbestos, absent actual disease, within statutory timeframe (Auburn High School); memos re employee liability in student transport in teachers' personal vehicles (Oneida), possible improper practice charge if transportation is required by district, need for insurance reimbursement; question of whether certain data processing employees can be considered exempt from the overtime provisions of the Fair Labor Standards Act (Onondaga BOCES); memo from the Syracuse Teachers Association with list of "do's and don'ts" for teachers accused of sexual misconduct, developed in consultation with law firm Blitman and King, in response to increase in number of sex abuse charges against teachers; letter from teacher at North Syracuse Teacher's Association re calculation of seniority for teachers who hold administrative positions for a time; memos re possible settlement of 3020a case against a teacher in the Liverpool Central School District; memos re Civil Service job classification in Oneida Central School District; chronology of events re charge of unfair representation issued against the Oswego County BOCES Supportive Association and NYSUT; Improper Practice Charges
- Utica Legal, 1985 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  Extensive materials re improper practice charge by school psychologist Don Brady against Rome Teachers Association, including PERB decision
- Western Legal, 1985 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  3020a case involving teacher who wore a pro-union tee-shirt to school and refused to take it off (misconduct and insubordination), also charged with inappropriate language in directing two students to cease a public display of affection (North Tonawanda Senior High); memo re payroll problems at Richford School District, including legal opinion that district was in violation of Education Law for contracting with banks that were not disbursing monies according to the wishes of the teachers; legal opinion that Niagara Falls school district could legally require physical examinations of its employees, but should pay for them; memo re teacher at Orchard Park, being required to teach outside his tenure area; material re dismissal in complex 3020a case at Hamburg High School, involving past sexual harassment charges against former principal; memos re retirement agreement in lieu of 3020a charges, attempt by Hamburg teacher to apply for retirement incentive plan; memo re Hamburg teacher removed from the preferred eligibility list after refusing an assignment because of pregnancy; memos re layoff of teacher at West Seneca, question of seniority rights; material re letter of admonishment to tenured Ellicottville teacher for taking military leave after being called up to active duty; 3020a case involving cocaine use, dismissal (Depew school district); 3020a case involving unprofessional behavior (outbursts of anger), Frewsburg district; PERB decision in Hamburg district re alleged violation of Taylor Law by refusing to continue employment of substitute teachers, memo from NYSUT attorney alleging subterfuge to prevent organizing; materials re 3020a charge against East Aurora teacher (immoral character; inappropriate physical contact); memos re 3020a charge against Batavia teachers (striking a student); memo discussing letter of reprimand against Cassadaga Valley teacher for not following procedural rules for corporal punishment, chance that challenge would result in 3020a charges and dismissal; memo re class load for teacher at West Seneca district; memo re teacher at North Tonawanda who wanted to come back from disability retirement, told it constituted resignation; miscellaneous 3020a cases; extensive materials re unemployment insurance decision appeal of regular substitute teacher Beth Abbott in Springville district
- Public Employees Federation (1 of 8), 1979-1982 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  Legal brief (with handwritten note, "case re Kramer") on behalf of respondent-appellant in Court of Appeals, CSEA v. Harold Newman et al., comprising the Public Employment Relations Board of the State of New York, the Public Employees Federation, AFL-CIO, James Northrup, as Acting Director of the Governor's Office of Employee Relations of the State of New York, Arthur Levitt, as Comptroller of the State of New York; legal brief (with NYSUT cover memo), on behalf of respondent-appellant-cross-respondent Public Employees Federation, AFL-CIO; handwritten note, "11/30/80 convicted mail fraud," noting 2-year sentence, other charges, "(1) defrauded state employee union, (2) rigged election, (3) channeled $ for election into slush fund & used money for own use"; long handwritten note titled, "Proposal," re Public Employee Federation's desire to resolve the John Kramer arbitration; Court of Appeals decision reversing Appellate Division decision, with NYSUT cover memo, March 27, 1979
- Public Employees Federation (2 of 8), 1982 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  Folder list of 24 items, including handwritten notes re dues promotion meetings, confidential PEF projected 1981-82 annual budget, NYSUT budget 1981-82; PEF memo re estimated expenditures, May 24, 1982; PEF 1982-83 Annual Budget with summaries of expenditures for each regional office; PEF memo re implementation of dues increase; sheet calculating increase in dues for years 1-3; narrative, "PEF Efforts to Avoid Layoffs"; annual PEF report reviewing professional legal services rendered by firm Cunningham & Sweeney on behalf of PEF, August 5, 1982; agreement by and between New York State Public Employees Federation, AFL-CIO (PEF), the American Federation of Teachers, AFL-CIO (AFT), and the Service Employees International Union, AFL-CIO and CLC (SEIU), September 25, 1979; minutes of PEF special Executive Board meeting, September 23, 1982; tentative agenda for PEF Executive Board meeting to be held October 10, 1982; memo to Jim Conti from NYSUT general counsel James Sandner, "Report on Status of PEF Cases Handled by NYSUT-OGC/NYC," October 4, 1982; memo to PRO MEMBER (Professionals for Membership Representation and Service) Executive Board Members re special Executive Board meeting, November 24, 1982; memo to PEF officers from PEF Budget Advisory Committee (BAC) re proposed dues increase for 1982 convention, October 5, 1982; minutes of PEF Legal Committee meeting, October 7., 1982; letter to delegates from PEF Secretary-Treasurer James J. Sheedy outlining reasons for pro posed dues increase; Division Report; PEF 4th Annual Convention Program, October 11-13, 1982; Memorandum of Understanding between the State of New York and the Public Employees Federation, AFL-CIO (PEF); PEF Agency Totals (total employees and total members, by agency); Negotiating Unit Profile II as of 11/81; UUP Projected Income from Dues, January 1979; list of NYSUT Public School Locals with Dues at least $100
- Public Employees Federation (3 of 8), 1982 (Box 21, Folder 3)